is there a general rule of thumb for how
to breathe during repetitions maybe even
strength versus hypertrophy in a way
that maximizes oxygen input to the
system you know keeps you uh alert and
conscious but that also protects the
body by creating some rigidity in the
system there's a a maneuver that is
labeled the vsol what that really means
is you're trying to use air to create
intraabdominal pressure and what you're
really trying to do is create a cylinder
around your spine the real issue you
have to to play here is regulation of
blood pressure and spinal stability now
you should be able to breathe and Brace
what I mean by that is you should be
able to create total intraabdominal
pressure regulate uh spine control while
breathing it's just very hard for a lot
of people to do it's it's a skill you
should absolutely work on um you can
actually you can do this and you can go
around like I do this trick in class and
students can come and like can push any
part um of
my entire abdomen is super tight and I
can talk now it's going to be a little
bit labored you can hear a little bit of
a difference but you should be able to
do that if you have to like hunch down
and you can't even muster a breath and
it takes that to create pressure you
don't really understand the abdominal
control necessary to create that
stability so step number one is that's
the goal now with the blood pressure
thing we have to be careful because a
standard blood pressure uh ideally if we
sat around right now is probably
something like 120 over 80 systolic
versus stolic that's a normal number
right high blood pressure is something
over that well with an acute bout of
exercise you can see that number reach
as high as like 450 over 350 which
effectively means you have total blood
occlusion right your blood pressure is
so high blood is not moving anywhere and
so in the middle of a very heavy set
especially complex movements especially
when they're loaded on your body um this
could be an overhead press or or squat
variations any like that blood pressure
is going to be a problem and the reason
why that matters is that's what's going
to make you pass out it's not the fact
that you ran out of oxy in 3 seconds
it's the fact that blood pressure got so
high you blacked out and so we want to
have we're going to have to play this
game of releasing a little bit of the
pressure so we can actually get blood to
move a little bit making sure that we
don't lose spinal stability um so we can
finish our workout that's really the
question you asked right how do I play
this game of oh I have several hundred
pounds on my back or my chest and I
don't want to
Exhale right so that I don't lose spinal
stability but at the same time I don't
want to pass out right which is which is
a problem so kind of a the rules of
thumb if you're going to be doing
something in which you can complete the
entire exercise without a breath and it
is of a maximal or close to load that's
probably your best strategy so in that
particular case you'll see a lot of
breathing techniques um where you're
going to take a very large inhale
ideally this is done through the abdomen
not the shoulders so we shouldn't seeing
clavicles Rising during this thing
you'll see a common mistake of of the
bars on their back and you see people do
this like big inhale thing and all they
do is Elevate their claves that's not
necessarily going to increase pressure
through the abdomen which is what you're
looking for so you want to be thinking
about belly moving out in all four areas
in front of you to your left and right
and to your back that's that quadrant
sort of idea of stabilizing your spine
you can do that independent of your
clavicles moving your shoulders don't
need to rise for that you don't really
need the oxygen for metabolic purposes
you're just using the air for a brace
that's really all you're after so you're
trying to visualize your torso as more
or less a cylinder yep and you're trying
to fill it with
air the logic being that if I were to
push down onto a say a a full unopened
can of soda yep water for all you sugar
phobes out there push as hard as I could
it's going to be hard for me to crush
that can but if the can were empty or if
it were a little bit kinked in the
middle correct then I could likely Crush
that can yeah what you're really doing
is you have your spinal Erectors in the
back right and then a whole series of
abdominal exercises and you actually
have some neural control Sy somatic
control of Contracting those but the you
don't have muscles on the inside that
you can do so you're basically bringing
in air and saying I'll use air to push
from the inside out and I'll use muscles
to push from the outside in to create
this brace and I don't want
overcompression with the muscles this is
a like if you if you see people that
have just enormous spinal
Erectors sometimes that's an indicator
of of actually a poor breathing or
bracing strategy because they're using
spinal rectors to create all their
compression and not actually using the
inside of enough it's not always the
case but sort of like a thing to think
about so you can fact like I'm doing it
right now and you'll see like a little
bit of a if you're really paying
attention to my voice you can hear a
little bit of a subtle difference but I
should be able to do this for quite a
long time right like I I I could take a
maximum rep right here in this position
whether I'm overhead pressing doing some
sort of row like anything and feel fairy
braced in in the entire quadrant this is
very helpful I I'm going to work on it
but can we say that a an effective way
to start off in terms of breathing
during repetitions would be to take a
gulp of air during the lowering phase
the Ecentric phase and then to Exhale
during the Y concentric exertion phase I
asked that because that's what I've been
doing for a while and it makes me feel
safe I don't know if I am and it allows
me to Exhale as I exert the the U
hardest portion of the exercise yeah and
perhaps I also borrowed that from
martial arts where one tends most often
is trained to Exhale on the on the Stu
yep if you're going to be doing again
the number of repetitions can be
completed without a breath a lot of the
times you're better off saving that
exhalation until you complete the idea
of holding my breath for an entire
compound set so again brings to mind um
you know like where is my insurance card
who's going to drive me to the hospital
this kind of thing um in all seriousness
what if I want to breathe during the set
I'm generally meaning if you're doing
like a one rep max or something like
that okay well then certainly I it hold
my breath for a one repetition maximum
that you know maybe like a double or
something like that depending on what
you're doing like maybe a triple a bench
breast you can probably do three and get
away with it a squat it gets harder
deadlift so it kind of depends on the
exercise um you want to take that be
breath though prior to the Ecentric
portion not during so up lower breathe
in lock we're set and now start our
movement pattern wherever it's going to
be um exhaling on the concentr portion
during it it is fine it's no problem um
especially if you're not extremely heavy
and what's your what are your thoughts
on grunting and screaming yeah fine I
don't care okay I don't tend to do that
I'm occasionally known to squeal or
whimper um but I do it person I do it
very quietly I think of you and I think
squeal whimper absolutely thanks um if
you're going to be doing multiple
repetitions uh what we actually do for
the NFL combine is we teach them a very
specific Excel strategy so there's one
test that they do uh which is they bench
press 225 lbs for as many reps as
possible a lot of these people will get
25 to 40 reps repetitions so we have a
very specific breathing pattern it would
be something like if we think that
they're going to do around 25 reps say
that's like our goal we might say okay
do the first 10 without without a breath
and then exhale reset and then do five
breath and then you might do five breath
three breath two breath and then one
breath per rep until we can't get any
more um so we'll have very specific
strategies for them um so what I would
say is is think about how many you're
going to complete and and then breathe
according uh to that and it tends to
increase in frequency as the number gets
closer to failure because you're going
to want that that err a little bit but
you just want to make sure that when you
re when you're breathing back in you're
in a safe spot so you don't want to be
catching that like rebreath when the
weight's on you you want to be in a
locked out position or away from you
when you're standing um so it tends to
be like at the end of the exercise not
in the middle of it um which is is going
to be a recipe for problems if you take
your breath then click the link in our
bio to get instant and free access to to
our hypertrophy highlights fireside chat
which is Dan and I discussing really
personal aspects of how we go about
programming for muscle hypertrophy in
that chat you're going to hear Dan and I
talk about our own experiences working
with clients who are trying to add
muscle mass and especially you're going
to hear us tell some stories that you've
never heard us talk about in any podcast
ever before this is not something you're
going to want to
miss